All right, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Today is our last day of
ערכין *Erachin* and, God willing, we will also make it our first
day of תמורה *Temurah*, get a דף ה *Daf Heh*, but we're
going to start now. This is דף ל"ד *Daf Lamed Daled*. We
start at the bottom of ל"ג עמוד ב *Lamed Gimmel amud bet*,
the first wide line. It's the end of the משנה mishnah *Mishna*.
The end of the משנה *Mishna* wraps up with houses in unwalled
cities and then went into the structure of the cities of the
לויים *Leviim* and changing the parks to the fields and to the
cities and so on, and keeping that structure. And now we end
with the last line which said the לויים *Leviim* can always sell,
which is not such a חידוש *Chidush*, and can always redeem. And
always redeem means that basically whatever they're selling, they can redeem it
starting at the beginning. It's not like fields that they have to
wait till the third year, and they can redeem it right up
to the יובל yovel *Yovel*. It's not like houses, so they always
have a right to redeem. Okay, so first wide line, הכהנים והלויים
מוכרים לעולם וגואלים לעולם *Hachohanim vehaleviim mocherim le'olam vegoalin le'olam*. תנו רבנן
Tanu rabanan: *Tanu Rabbanan*, our rabbis taught, גאולת עולם geulat olam תהיה
ללויים *Geulat olam tihyeh laleviim*, an eternal redemption the לויים *Leviim* shall
have. מה תלמוד לומר mah talmud lomar? *Mah Talmud lomar*, what does
that teach you? לפי שנאמר *Lefi shene'emar*, because it says, מספר שני
תבואות ימכור לך *Mispar shenei tevuot yimkor lach*, that by a normal
field of a שדה אחוזה sedeh achuza *Sedeh achuza* that you sell
it for at least two years, that's how חז"ל *Chazal* read that
פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk*. יכול אף זה כן *Yachol af zeh ken*, maybe
a field of a לוי Levi *Levi* also, he has to wait
two years before he can redeem. תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*, גאולת עולם
ge'ulat olam תהיה ללויים *Geulat olam tihyeh laleviim*. No, at all times.
Meaning, even from the very beginning. Even a field can be at
the beginning. ולפי שנאמר *Ulefi shene'emar*, and because it also says by
fields of a normal Israel, ויצא השדה ביובל קודש להשם כשדה החרם
*Veyatza hasadeh bavu vekodesh l'Hashem kesedeh hacherem*, that if he sanctified the
field and somebody else bought it, what happens at the יובל yovel
*Yovel*? It goes to the כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim*. יכול אף זה כן
*Yachol af zeh ken*, perhaps even this is true that a field
of a לוי Levi *Levi* that he sanctified, now we're not talking
about sale, that he sanctified, and a Israel buys, perhaps also it
goes to the כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim*. So תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*, the
verse teaches, גאולת עולם ge'ulat olam תהיה ללויים *Geulat olam tihyeh laleviim*.
No, they can always redeem. Now, of course, what's not clear is,
so what happens? So the guy who redeemed it off הקדש *Hekdesh*,
he holds on to it until I, the לוי Levi *Levi*, have
a chance to redeem it? Presumably. If the תורה *Torah* isn't saying
it goes to the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*, then where does it stay?
It stays in the hands of the person who bought it off
הקדש *Hekdesh* and then I, however, as a לוי Levi *Levi*, always
have a chance to redeem it. Of course, there's another possibility. The
other possibility is come the יובל yovel? *Yovel*, I get it back
directly. But anyway the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* isn't being clear, but presumably
the גאולה *Geula* means the right to redeem it and it stays
in the hands of the person who bought it off הקדש *Hekdesh*.
Couldn't it also go to another כהן kohen *Kohen*, another כהנים kohanim
*Kohanim* and then he could redeem it from the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*?
I suppose, right. I suppose that's possible too. Yeah, although that would
really be a stretch because again the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is sort
of saying that this גאולת עולם *Geulat olam* overrides what the תורה
*Torah* has described. But you know but it's an interesting it's an
interesting yeah again it's not clear.
Is this right to redeem of the לויים *Leviim* unlimited or inheritable?
Well, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discussed it yesterday whether it's limited to
their ערי הלויים *Arei ha-Leviim* and is it limited to a לוי
Levi *Levi*. So one opinion said you need it to be both
a לוי Levi *Levi* and ערי לויים arei leviyim. *Arei Leviim* and
the other said it just had to be ערי לויים arei leviyim.
*Arei Leviim*. So now you mean if this לוי Levi *Levi* dies
can his son.
That's an interesting question. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discussed that by בתי
ערי חומה batei arei choma. *Battei arei chomah*. Presumably yes, because the
only criteria was that it was ערי הלויים *Arei ha-Leviim* and בתי
*Battei*, although obviously a different לוי *Levi* completely unrelated cannot redeem from
another לוי *Levi*. It's an interesting question. I don't know. So much
of the details are not spelled out, which is just proof about
how we're dealing, you know, with an area that was, A, not
practiced and, B, just because it wasn't practiced isn't enough of a
reason. I mean, my God, you have the huge מסכתות *Masechtot* of
קדשים Kodashim. *Kodashim* and זבחים *Zevachim* and מנחות *Menachot*,
but for some reason this did not receive the same type of
detailed treatment. So a lot of those gaps are not spelled out.
Okay, now, לפי שנאמר *Lefi shene'emar*, because it says, וקם הבית אשר
בעיר אשר לו חומה לצמיתות *Ve-kam ha-bayit asher ba-ir asher lo chomah
litzmitut*,
but if it's a house in a walled city you can, after
the year, you lose it completely. יכול אף זה כן *Yachol af
zeh ken*, maybe this as well. תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*, גאולת עולם
תהיה ללויים *Geulat olam tihyeh laleviim*. No, you can redeem it at
all times, so even if it's after the year, you can redeem.
And presumably, not like when we discussed by a house in an
unwalled city that there was a question of the gap here, right,
the middle year between the second year and so on, here it's
not saying you have laws of houses and laws of fields, here
it's just saying across the board you always can redeem. Okay, so
even in year two, whatever, none of that would matter. בשלמא הני
תרתי לחי *Bishlama hani tarti lachai*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says the
first two I understand what the חידוש *Chidush* is, אלא Ela... בתי
ערי חומה batei arei choma. ללויים מי אית להו *Ela battei arei
chomah laleviim mi it lehu*, the second one in a way I
understand the חידוש *Chidush* but I don't understand the scenario. How would
a לוי *Levi* ever have a house in a walled city? Why
not? והתניא ve-hatanya, *Ve-hatanya*, we taught in a ברייתא *Baraita*, ערים הללו
*Arim halalu*, these cities, meaning ערי מקלט Arei Miklat *Arei miklat*, this
is a ברייתא *Baraita* in מכות *Makkot*, אין עושים אותם לא כפרים
קטנים ולא כרכים גדולים *En osim otam lo kefarim ketanim velo kerachim
gedolim*. You don't make them too small villages because obviously if the
person, the גואל *Goel*, the accidental murderer, the accidental murderer has to
go there and he has to stay there. If it's a tiny
little village, he's not going to have enough provisions for himself and,
you know, it's a place if you're living in a little village
then you have to go to the bigger cities from time to
time and this person. has to stay there. So you don't make
ערי מקלט Arei Miklat. little villages, and but you also don't make
them major metropolises. Why don't you make them major metropolises? So רש״י
Rashi says because you know if a major metropolis like New York
City, who the heck knows, you know, you can't keep track of
who's in and who's out, and it'll be way too easy for
the גואל הדם Goel HaDam to sneak in and to kill this
person. So you have to make them reasonable middle-sized cities.
So therefore,
okay, אלא ערים בינוניות, ella arim beinoniyot, middle-sized towns, like not villages,
not cities, towns. Anyway, so presumably that includes the idea, although it's
not explicit, that it's unwalled. Okay, if what's- what do you wall?
You wall things that are going to be your major metropolises, your
major cities. So presumably, you'll never have a walled city. So again,
the גמרא Gemara could have just had a couple of obvious answers.
One answer is, okay, it was a little village and happened to
be walled, I mean not a village, it was a town, but
it happened to be walled. Or it could say, you know, that
maybe it had a wall- it had a wall at the time
of יהושע בן נון Yehoshua Bin Nun and then the wall fell
down. Maybe it's יריחו, Yericho, maybe they made יריחו Yericho an עיר
מקלט. Ir Miklat. I don't remember, the ערי מקלט Arei Miklat are
listed. I don't remember if שכם Shechem is an עיר מקלט. Ir
Miklat. Anyway, so let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara
says. But how could you have a לוי of a walled city?
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, לא
קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult.
כאן שהוקף ולבסוף ישב, כאן שישב ולבסוף הוקף. kan she-hukaf u-levasof yashav,
kan she-yashav u-levasof hukaf. No, it's not difficult, if one is that
first had a wall and then was settled, the other it was
settled and it then had a wall. So what does that mean?
That means that
one minute,
right, means that basically the answer that the second answer I suggested,
they came in in the time of יהושע Yehoshua and they- it
didn't have a wall, so meaning- but reverse that- they- they designated
it as an עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, it was designated because it
didn't have a wall and later they built a wall. So the
גמרא Gemara says, one minute, if it didn't have a wall initially,
then it doesn't have the status of a walled city. וכי האי
גוונא מי הוי חומה? ve-chi hai gavna mi havei choma? Does that
count as a wall? והתניא, ואיש כי ימכר בית מושב עיר חומה.
ve-ish ki yimkor beit moshav ir choma. If a man sells a
house in a walled city, what does that mean, a walled city?
It means שהוקף ולבסוף ישב, she-hukaf u-levasof yashav, it has to start
with the wall and then be settled, ולא שישב ולבסוף הוקף, ve-lo
she-yashav u-levasof hukaf, and not that it was settled and then had
a wall. יכול אפילו הקיפוה ישראל? Yachol afilu hikifuha Yisrael? Now it
goes on, maybe if- let's say, to determine when it had a
wall, maybe it means when the Jews put up a wall? So
maybe they went into the land of Israel and then they put
up a wall, that should be good, because even if it's first
settled and then the wall, at least the wall was erected by
Jews, and therefore that gives it extra status. No, נאמר כאן חומה
ונאמר להלן חומה. ne-emar kan choma ve-ne-emar lehallan choma. It says wall
here, it says there wall. It says wall when it says that
they conquered the cities in עבר הירדן, Ever HaYarden, it says sixty
cities all surrounded by a wall.
מה להלן עובדי כוכבים, ma lehallan ovdei kochavim, the same way there
it means the non-Jews surrounded with
wall, אף כאן עובדי כוכבים, af kan ovdei kochavim, here too. So
actually the status here is given דוקא davka by the non-Jews. So
it- what you walked in with, the cities that had a wall,
not by you, by the non-Jews, and that first a wall was
made and then was settled, those are the cities of מוקף חומה.
mukaf choma. יכול אפילו הקיפוה עובדי כוכבים אחר כך? yachol afilu hikifuha
ovdei kochavim achar kach? Maybe let's say the non-Jews made a wall
afterwards, meaning first it was settled and then the wall was made?
Or first you came into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and then the
wall was
made? So נאמר להלן חומה ונאמר כאן חומה. ne-emar lehallan choma ve-ne-emar
kan choma. No, it says wall in both cases again, the wall
that it says
by the walled cities that they conquered in
עבר הירדן, Ever HaYarden, מה להלן עובדי כוכבים קודם לכן, ma lehallan
ovdei kochavim kodem lachen, the same way there it means it had
a walled city before you got there, אף כאן עובדי כוכבים קודם
לכן. af kan ovdei kochavim kodem lachen. Here too, walled- a wall
prior. So basically, the only thing that counts as a walled city
is the city that when you came into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
were- had a wall and that wall preceded them having been, you
know, when it was built up hundreds of years ago, the wall
came first and then the city. So the only thing we can
count as a walled city for the הלכה halacha of houses in
a walled city is walled cities when you came in in the
time of יהושע. Yehoshua. And presumably, that's also what- when we were
deciding when there were the ערי מקלט. Arei Miklat, I mean, it
is, if you read יהושע, Yehoshua, they decided the ערי מקלט at
the time of יהושע. Yehoshua. So you can't separate the times. Okay,
like I said, the only possibility might have been יריחו, Yericho, right,
because it did have a wall and then it fell down and
then they could have- anyway, but other than that, so how are
you going to get something that they made an עיר מקלט Ir
Miklat and that at the same time was a walled city, if
it all happened at the time of יהושע? Yehoshua? So תרגם רב
יוסף בריה דרב סלא חסידה קמיה דרב פפא, Tirgem Rav Yosef breih
de-Rav Sala Chasida kammih de-Rav Pappa, כגון שנפלו להם, kegon she-naflu lahem,
as- the- כגון שנפלו להם, kegon she-naflu lahem, הן ומגרשיהן. hen u-migresheihen.
So one minute, right, meaning what happened was, נפלו naflu here does
not mean the walls fell down. נפלו naflu means that it was-
it- it fell into their lot, that, you know what? You're right.
You're not supposed to have an עיר מקלט Ir Miklat as a
לוי city. But what happens when they were distributing the cities and
if they drew lots to randomly assign the ערי מקלט, right, what
would happen if it happened to be that, whoops, the- the name
that got pulled out for your city at the- as לוי happened
to have a wall? So what are you going to do? But
we're not supposed to have a wall. We're not supposed to be
a big city. So you'd think the answer would be, you knock
down the wall. So basically, they're saying... randomly got assigned to be
the לוי so there's a problem about making the עיר מקלט ir
miklat so maybe they knocked down the wall? Okay so let's take
a look. נפלו להם ממגרשיהם naflu lahem mimigrasheihem they and their surrounding
area. The גמרא Gemara says הינו מגרש והסביבנו קיימו. heinu migrash vehasvivenu
kaimu. The גמרא Gemara says one minute והא סביב דעל המיסביבנו קיימי?
veha saviv de'al hamisivenu kaimi? But one minute but then it would
be that when it fell to them the plan was to knock
down the wall to make it a wall for the sake of
being an עיר מקלט. ir miklat. Okay so and meaning presumably then
when you actually got around to knocking down the wall it would
no longer have the status of בתי ערי חומה. Now that's a
question because if you remember we said that even if the wall
fell down later and it seems like a perfect answer. It had
the wall then they knocked it down so it served as an
עיר מקלט ir miklat and because it had the wall originally it
served as a house in בתי ערי חומה. But let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes with this. So the גמרא Gemara says תוספות
Tosafot by the way asks that question. תוספות Tosafot says who cares
that it fell down later but the גמרא Gemara is not so
much focused on that so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב אשי אצטריך. Amar Rav Ashi
itzterich. No you still need it. Here's the scenario. סלקא דעתך אמינא
עד דסתרי סתרי Salika datchach amina ad desatri satri right until you've
knocked down the wall. So you've got this city. It's able to
be an עיר מקלט ir miklat because you're planning on knocking down
the wall but until you get around to knocking down the wall
maybe then if you sell your house in it it has the
status of a house sold in an עיר ir in a walled
city. אם מזדבני לחלטיה im mizdabni lechlatiyeh and if you sell it
it gets after the year goes fully over to the purchaser. קא
משמע לן ka mashma lan that it doesn't that they can always
redeem it. Okay so the גמרא has a real challenge a real
problem that even though the principle is clear a לוי can always
redeem it. What's not clear is how do you have a scenario
of a לוי selling a house in a walled city if the
עיר מקלט ir miklat were knocked down. And he has an answer
that okay but you knock the they had the walled city but
the plan was to take down the wall. Again the interesting question
is that that would have been a perfect answer because as we
said for definition of walled city you go by the time of
יהושע Yehoshua it doesn't matter if it fell afterwards. For some reason
the גמרא did not say that here. תוספות Tosafot raises that question.
Okay now we move on. תנו רבנן: כשדה החרם לכהן תהיה אחוזתו.
kisdeh hacharem lacohen tihiyeh achuzato. Now we're going back remember if a
ישראל Yisrael sanctifies his שדה אחוזה sdeh achuza. what happens when the
יובל yovel and it's redeemed by somebody else? What happens when the
יובל yovel hits? It goes to the כהנים. Kohanim It says like
a חרם cherem field it goes to the כהנים. Kohanim, מה תלמוד
לומר? What does it teach me? Why does it connect
this
to
a
field of חרם? cherem? So this
is really just
quoting a גמרא we had before it's almost word for word. הואיל
ומצאנו לכהן ho'il umatzanu lacohen so tell me another הלכה. halacha.
Not the
הלכה halacha
about
what happens when you sanctify a
field but what happens when a כהן kohen sanctifies a field? Here
we're discussing it of course because we're discussing
the
כהנים
ולויים kohanim uleviyim
in their field. So we emphasize selling
now we're talking about sanctifying. מה תלמוד לומר מניין לכהן שהקדיש שדה
חרמו? mah talmud lomar minayin lacohen shehikdish sedeh cheramo? How do you
know if
a כהן kohen's sanctifies a field of his
not from the ערי
הלוויים arei haleviyim but a field that he got through a ישראל
Yisrael a field
he got
because it was made into a חרם cherem and now it became
his field? So how do you know שלא יאמר הואיל ויוצא לכהנים
shelo yomar ho'il veyotzei lacohanim look guys I'm sanctifying this what's going
to happen when it comes to the יובל? yovel? It's going to
get divided by all the כהנים Kohanim okay? והרי היא veharei hi
so now by the way let me point out something here that's
implicit. Why does it give the scenario when it wants to know
what happens to a כהן's kohen field when he sanctifies it when
the יובל yovel. hits? Why did they just say if he sanctified
part of his portion in the ערי הלוויים? arei haleviyim? What happens
when the יובל yovel hits? And the answer is no we already
know that. That's what our משנה says. If it was from the
ערי הלוויים arei haleviyim and he sanctified it then it says גאולת
עולם you then it stays the way it is and he can
always redeem it right that's the basic point. Things don't transfer to
other people whatever even they go back
to him or he can redeem it. הא ha but what if
it wasn't from the ערי הלוויים? arei haleviyim? What if it was
a field that's considered his permanently not from ערי הלוויים? arei haleviyim?
How does he get a permanent field not from ערי הלוויים? arei
haleviyim? Because a ישראל Yisrael made something חרם cherem and then that
transferred to him right or a ישראל Yisrael sanctified something and it
was redeemed by another ישראל Yisrael and then it transferred to him.
Now he has this permanently right it's not going back to anybody
else but it's not an עיר לויים. ir leviyim. Okay so what
is going to be? You got to have that like its own
category. It's permanently his but it's not ערי לויים. arei leviyim Now
he sanctifies it. So now we're not going to treat it like
ערי לויים. arei leviyim He sanctified it. What's going to happen יובל?
Yovel It'll get distributed to the כהנים Kohanim just like when a
ישראל Yisrael sanctifies his field. What happens? It's because any other citizen
it's treated as a because his purchase was as any other citizen
we're going to treat him
yeah although no if it were a purchase this whole הלכה halacha
wouldn't apply that's why I emphasized permanently. A purchased field you cannot
determine its fate because of the יובל. Yovel But right because his
relationship to it I mean in a way he did get it
by virtue of being a כהן Cohen, so I wouldn't say as
any other citizen. But because it's not ערי לויים Arei Leviim, it
has the normal status. So he sanctifies it right and therefore because
it's not ערי לויים Arei Leviim come the יובל Yovel it's going
to get distributed to the כהנים Kohanim. but that's why we're giving
a scenario
Okay, now he comes with a claim, hey look guys, it's going
to go to the כהנים Kohanim anyway, I'm a כהן, Cohen, I
might as well keep it. Very nice claim. Okay he says like
this: והיה השדה בצאתו ביובל קדש לה' כשדה החרם, Vehaya hasadeh betzeito
bayovel kodesh l'Hashem kesadeh hacharem, it's going to go to the כהנים,
Kohanim. והרי היא תחת ידי, v'harei hi tachat yadi, and anyway it's
mine, I mean it's not yours now you've sanctified it but it
was yours, תהא שלי, tehei sheli, let me just keep it. ודין
הוא, Vedin hu, and it makes sense, בשל אחרים אני זוכה, beshel
acherim ani zocheh, if I'm going to get other people's fields, of
course there you only are one of the people that you know
you with a thousand others, but okay, if I'll get other people's
fields, בשלי לא כל שכן, besheli lo kol sheken, how much more
so should I just keep this field that used to be mine.
תלמוד לומר והיה השדה בצאתו ביובל קדש לה' כשדה החרם, Talmud lomar
vehaya hasadeh betzeito bayovel kodesh l'Hashem kesadeh hacharem, that the field of
the ישראל Yisrael that goes in the יובל Yovel that was sanctified
goes to the כהנים Kohanim like the חרם Cherem field. וכי מה
למדנו משדה החרם מעתה? Vechi mah lamadnu misdeh hacharem me'atah? Why is
it comparing it to a חרם Cherem field? What's the relevance? הרי
זה בא ללמד ונמצא למד. Harei zeh ba lilamed venimtza lamed. It
looks like the חרם Cherem is coming to teach something to the
case of the ישראל, Yisrael, but it's really the opposite. It's really
learning from something from the case of the ישראל. Yisrael. מקיש שדה
חרמו לשדה אחוזה של ישראל. Makish sdeh charmo lisdeh achuza shel Yisrael.
It connects a שדה חרם sdeh cherem of a כהן, Cohen which
again is his permanent field, but not as ערי לויים, Arei Leviim
and it connects it to a field that was sanctified by ישראל,
Yisrael, a שדה אחוזה. sdeh achuza They have basically the same law.
Okay, מה שדה אחוזה של ישראל יוצא מידו ומתחלק לכהנים, Mah sdeh
achuza shel Yisrael yotzei miyado umitchalek lakohanim,
the same way a שדה אחוזה sdeh achuza, that was sanctified by
ישראל Yisrael and redeemed, what happened to it? On the יובל Yovel
it gets divided to the כהנים Kohanim and it leaves his control.
אף שדה חרמו, Af sdeh charmo, even this permanent field of a
כהן Cohen, that's not ערי לויים Arei Leviim. that he got because
it was a שדה חרם sdeh cherem and went to him, what
will happen to it if it's sanctified? On when the יובל comes
along, יוצא מידו ומתחלק לאחיו הכהנים. Yotzei miyado umitchalek leachiv hakohanim. He
has no special status, gets divided equally to the כהנים. Kohanim. So
that's very nice. What this also functions here to do in a
nice way is as I said to hold in sharp relief his
relationship to ערי לויים Arei Leviim and the relationship to שדה חרמו.
sdeh charmo. שדה חרמו Sdeh charmo they get permanently, becomes like their
שדה אחוזה, sdeh achuza, but it's not like ערי לויים. Arei Leviim,
So ערי לויים arei Levi'im, you sell or you sanctify, you always
לגאולת עולם תהיה, ligeulat olam tihyeh, you can always redeem. שדה חרמו,
Sdeh charmo, which the כהנים get and it becomes their שדה אחוזה,
sdeh achuza right, or you could say the fields that they got
because the יובל hit and these fields of ישראל Yisrael that were
sanctified were distributed, these things that they get that become their שדה
אחוזה sdeh achuza. but are not ערי לויים, arei Levi'im, those get
treated like the ישראל Yisrael שדה אחוזה. sedei achuza Okay, and those
things if they're sanctified get divided by the כהנים. Okay, now we
go on.
אמר מר, Amar mar, בשל חרמי אני זוכה, beshel cheremi ani zocheh,
here was his claim: Hey, I'm going to get other people's fields,
I might as well keep mine. Says מי דמי? mi dami? What
type of claim is that? התם זוכה בעלמא, Hatam zocheh be'alma, there
you merit it, meaning you're one of a thousand כהנים that have
the right to get that field. הכא קא שקיל ליה, Hacha ka
shakil lei, here you want to keep the whole thing. Okay, you're
זוכה zocheh by others, you're זוכה zocheh by this, you're one of
a group. But your claim was right to say, since I'm one
of a group there, I should get the whole thing here. What
type of claim is that?
So אמר רמי בר חמא איצטריך, Amar Rami bar Chama itztarich, no,
we still needed the פסוק, he still could have made a claim.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka datach amina, הוה כתיב, hava ketiv, ואיש את
קדשיו לו יהיו, ve'ish et kodashav lo yihiyu, that a man, a
כהן, Cohen gets to keep his sacrifices. What does it mean? If
a כהן Cohen shows up in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and
he's bringing a קרבן, korban, he could actually say, "Hey, you know
what, I'm going to bring my this קרבן korban today and I'm
going to be the one that eats the meat." So since you're
a כהן Cohen you have a right to basically bring your own
קרבנות korbanot and keep them. So therefore הכא נמי כי קדשיו דמיא,
hacha nami ki kodashav damya, maybe this is like it. You know,
the same way if you're a כהן Cohen, you could say, "I'll
bring my קרבן korban and benefit from it." So I'm a כהן,
Cohen I sanctified my field, so I'll also be the כהן Cohen
that's at the receiving end, at the other end when the יובל
hits. Okay, so there's a certain analogy. So it says מי דמי?
mi dami? קדשיו לאו ברשותו הכא ברשותו, Kodashav lav birshuto hacha birshuto,
your קרבנות korbanot are not yours, here it's yours now. What do
you mean? So if anything that's a reason why you should have
more right here, it's a better argument, this field started as mine.
But somehow the גמרא's question is that no, by the קרבנות, korbanot,
you are getting it by virtue of not it having been yours.
Why do you get to keep the קרבן korban when you bring
them? By virtue of having done the עבודה. avodah. Your basic right
is to choose to do the עבודה avodah with your קרבן. korban.
And then you're awarded the קרבן korban by the meat by having
done the עבודה. avodah. Here, basically, it starts as an issue of
ownership and once you sanctify it, there is nothing that entitles you
to be getting it at the other end. Okay, so it's a
little funny way of phrasing it, but the basic point is that
here, there, what entitles you to get it at the other end
is you did the עבודה. avodah. Here, nothing entitles you to get
it at the other end, so why do you think that you
have a special right? So the גמרא says... Yes, does he have
the right to
choose which כהן Kohen does his קרבן? korban? Wouldn't that entitle him
to right?
No, no, no. So you're right, obviously he has some more rights
there, but the basic point is that in the end why you're
why you're getting the meat is because you've done the עבודה. avodah.
אלא... אלא אמר רב נחמן איצטריך, Ella amar Rav Nachman itztrikh, he
still needs it. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Sal'ka da'atakh amina, I would have
thought his share could be his claim. הואיל וכתיב כאחוזת עולם היא
להם, Hoil u'ketiv ka'achuzat olam hi lahem, that it is an eternal
inheritance for them, and this is really the point of, this is
why it's being brought here. The same way a לוי and כהן
have, you know, גאולת עולם by their ערי לויים, arei Levi'im? by
the stuff that really is theirs, I mean not really is theirs
but you know is the ערי לויים, arei Levi'im? and there they
can always redeem, הא נמי אחוזתו? Ha nami achuzato? Maybe the things
that they get permanently that are not ערי לויים? arei Levi'im, What
do they get permanently that are not ערי לויים? arei Levi'im, Something
that was made חרם cherem that goes to כהנים or something that
was sanctified and not redeemed and then goes to the כהנים. Those
things we've been learning are theirs and are theirs permanently. So that's
really the הוה אמינא. hava amina. Maybe everything that is their permanent
inheritance, not just ערי לויים, they have the same rights to? קא
משמע לן אחוזתו, Ka mashma lan achuzato, only their real inheritance. אחוזתו
אין חרם לא. Achuzato in cherem lo. Also when it's something that's
their real inheritance, ערי לויים, that's when we said גאולת עולם and
there they can always redeem, it doesn't get divided if they sanctify
it, they always have the right to get that back. However, other
things that they get permanently that we've been learning about in this
last פרק, perek, חרם, cherem, סתם הקדש, stam hekdesh, and so on,
those are things that they basically have the same status as a
שדה אחוזה of a ישראל. Yisrael. הדרן עלך המוכר שדהו וסליקא לה
מסכת ערכין. Hadran alakh hamocher sadehu uslika lah Masechet Arachin. So יישר
כח yasher koach to everybody! That was a very fun מסכת, masechet,
I would say. A מסכת masechet that had a lot of fascinating
topics I think we never would have expected to come up in
קדשים.
And now we will end that for now and in one minute
we'll then start.